Mike Schaekermann

49 Columbia St W, Unit 101 Waterloo, ON N2L 3K4 mschaeke@uwaterloo.ca +1 (647) 573-2908

https://cs.uwaterloo.ca/~mschaeke/

OVERVIEW

My research interest is at the intersection of machine learning and human-computer interaction. In particular, I look at how the power of human and machine intelligence may be combined to solve problems too hard to be tackled by computational methods alone. My work in this topic revolves around the analysis of medical time series data.

EDUCATION

Ph.D. Candidate

2016 - Present

University of Waterloo, ON, Canada

Computer Science

Advisors: Edith Law and Kate Larson

Bachelor of Science in Engineering

2014

Salzburg University of Applied Sciences, Austria

Media Informatics

Thesis Supervisor: Lennart Nacke

Staatsexamen (equivalent to Bachelors)

2011

University of Marburg, Germany

Medicine

AWARDS & HONOURS

David R. Cheriton Graduate Scholarship (\$10,000) — UWaterloo	2016
International Doctoral Student Award (\$11,760/year) — UWaterloo	2016
Merit-based Scholarship — Salzburg University of Applied Sciences	2014
Merit-based Scholarship for Foreign Studies	2014
Engineering Scholarship — both Economic Chamber of Salzburg	2013
Nominee for the German National Academic Foundation	2009

WORKING PAPER

Sequence-aware Active Learning for Sleep Stage Classification. Schaekermann, M., Pineau, J., Lim, A., Poupart, P., Nacke, L. E. & Law, E.

POSITION PAPERS

Resolvable vs. Irresolvable Ambiguity: A New Hybrid Framework for Dealing with Uncertain Ground Truth. Schaekermann, M., Law, E., Williams, A. C., & Callaghan, W. Workshop on Human-Centered Machine Learning at SIGCHI 2016. San Jose, CA.

Repidly: A Lightweight Tool for the Collaborative Analysis of Biosignals and Gameplay Videos. Schaekermann, M., Nacke, L. E. Workshop on Lightweight GUR for Indies and Non-Profit Organizations at SIGCHI 2016. San Jose, CA.

The Big Picture: Preserving Context in the Decomposition of Complex Expert Tasks. Williams, A. C., Bradshaw, J., Schaekermann, M., Tse, T., Callaghan, W., & Law, E. Workshop on Microproductivity at SIGCHI 2016. San Jose, CA.

PRESEN-TATIONS

Resolvable vs. Irresolvable Ambiguity: A New Hybrid Framework for Dealing with Uncertain Ground Truth. (see above)

Workshop on Human-Centered Machine Learning at SIGCHI, San Jose, CA.

Hacking Brain-Computer Interfaces

2015

2016

Singularity Meets Self-Improvement (SMSI) Meetup, Berlin, Germany

Implicit Surface Modeling for 3D Printing

2015

WebGL Meetup, Berlin, Germany

WORK EXPERIENCE

Entrepreneur

2011 - 2015

SpontaneousOrder GmbH, Berlin, Germany

- Co-founder and Head of IT of a startup company dealing with browser-based designs for 3D-printing (https://stilnest.com/)
- Received USD 1 million in seed funding in 08/2014 (https://www.crunchbase.com/organization/stilnest), followed by additional funding rounds
- Led a medium-sized team of software engineers to build an international platform for 3D-printed designer accessories

Visiting Researcher

2013 - 2014

Games and Media Entertainment Research Laboratory University of Ontario Institute of Technology, ON, Canada

Tutor for Applied Mathematics

2012 - 2013

Salzburg University of Applied Sciences, Austria

Research Assistant at Core-Unit "BrainImaging"

2009 - 2010

University Medical Center, Marburg, Germany

SELECTED PROJECTS

CrowdEEG

Framework to combine machine and human intelligence for the scalable and accurate analysis of human clinical EEG recordings. This is an active research project in the HCI CrowdLab at the University of Waterloo, Canada, led by professor Edith Law.

3D Simulation of the Human Endocrine System

Real-time 3D simulation of the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis, a part of the human neuro-endocrine system. This was done as final project for a course on "Simulation Methods in Physiology and Neurobiology" at the medical school of the University of Marburg, Germany.

Repidly

Collaborative web application for annotating gameplay videos, based on physiological time series data developed as part of my bachelor thesis at Salzburg University of Applied Sciences, Austria.

Implicit Surface Modeling for 3D Printing

Web application enabling real-time customization and animation of 3D-printable objects. It makes use of implicit surfaces, raymarching and the iso-surface extraction algorithm Marching Cubes.

TECHNOLOGY SKILLS

Programming Languages: C++, Java, C#, Assembler, Python.

Web Development: HTML5, CSS3, JavaScript, Nginx, Apache, Node.js, Meteor,

Django, MongoDB, PostgreSQL, MySQL, AWS, Heroku.

Machine Learning / AI: Decision Trees, kNN, Generalized Linear Models, Logistic Regression, Support Vector Machines, Gaussian Process, Neural Networks, Informed, Local & Adversarial Search, Constraint Satisfaction Problems, (Partially Observable)

Markov Decision Processes, Multi-armed Bandits, Reinforcement Learning.

Game Development: Game Engine Architecture, Advanced Collision Detection. Augmented Reality: Filters, Object Tracking, Feature Points (SIFT, SURF). Computer Graphics: Programmable Graphics Pipeline, OpenGL/WebGL and

Shader Programming with GLSL, Marching Cubes.

SERVICE & **LEADERSHIP** Reviewer for Conferences: CHI PLAY (2016) Membership: Association for Computing Machinery

Involvement with Academic Institution: Advisor for incoming international students (2012), President of the students council (2013) at Salzburg University of Applied Sciences, Austria

INTER-NATIONAL **EXPERIENCE** International PhD Student

University of Waterloo, ON, Canada

International Visiting Researcher

2013 - 2014

University of Ontario Institute of Technology, ON, Canada

Advisor for Incoming International Students

Salzburg University of Applied Sciences, Austria

International Student at Academic High School

Avondale College, Auckland, New Zealand

LANGUAGE SKILLS

English - Full Professional Proficiency

German - Native Speaker

French, Italian, Japanse, Maori - Basics

2012

2007

2016 - Present

TOEFL iBT (116/120)